Guide to the Ann Feinstein Collection of New York City Prints 1850-2003 PR 300
New-York Historical Society
Ann Feinstein collection of New York City prints
1850-2003
New-York Historical Society
Feinstein, Ann
PR 300
2.04 Linear feet (4 boxes)
Collection of fine art and commercial prints depicting New York City scenes and views. Includes etching, lithographs and other printmaking processes.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David Feinstein, 2013
Arrangement
This collection is organized in two series:
Series I: Fine Art Prints (arranged by artist)
Series II: Commercial Prints (arranged by publication)
The finding aid is arranged intellectually, while the physical materials are arranged by size. As a result, box numbers within the finding aid may not be consecutive.
Related Materials
Similar works by the artists represented in this collection (and other artists) can be found in the Fine Art Prints of New York Collection, PR 299, the Printmaker File, PR 58, and the James Boyd Collection of New York City Etchings, PR 7.
Scope and Contents
The Ann Feinstein Collection of New York City Prints includes approximately 150 prints that span the nineteenth, twentieth and twenty-first centuries. It is divided into two series: Fine Art Prints and Commercial Prints.
Fine Art Prints are arranged by artist. Most of the prints are etchings; a small number of lithographs, aquatints and linoleum cuts are also included. The prints depict buildings and scenes in New York City. Titles are listed in the finding aid.
Commercial Prints consist primarily of illustrations for the pictorial press and are arranged by publication. Loose newspaper illustrations (mainly from Harper's Weekly) depict urban experiences in the 19th century, including tenements, the homeless and street people. A few full issues of Harper's and Frank Leslie's are also included. In addition, this series includes Parts 1 through 5 of the 1875 edition of Old New York from the Battery To Bloomingdale, with illustrations by Eliza Greatorex.
Separated Materials
Reproduction prints from Valentine's Manual and King's New York handbook; three trade cards from the Singer Sewing Company; and a few prints depicting scenes in England, have been separated and added to the Geographic File, PR 20.
Aquatints (prints); Etchings (prints); Linocuts; Lithographs.; Prints (visual works).; Skyscrapers -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; Streets -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; Subways -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 19th century.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.
- Series I: Fine Art Prints
  - Subseries I.1: ARIKE, Michael (b. 1933)
    - Chrysler and Beyond, 2001 (Offsite-box 3)
    - Twilight in Manhattan, 2006 (Offsite-box 3)
  - Subseries I.2: DEVILLE, Henry Wilfrid (b. 1871) (Offsite-box 1)
    - The Game of Marbles, undated (Offsite-box 1)
  - Subseries I.3: DI CERBO, Michael (b. 1947)
    - Bird's Eye Perspective, 2006 (Offsite-box 3)
  - Subseries I.4: DOLICE, Leon (1892-1960)
    - First Street and Bowery (Offsite-box 1)
  - Subseries I.5: GREATOREX, Eliza Pratt (1819-1897) (Offsite-box 1)
    - Old New York-No. 1 Broadway., 1874 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Old Jersey Ferry House, Corner of Greenwich and Cedar Streets., 1875 (Offsite-box 1)
    - St. Paul's Church., 1875 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Old New York-Through the Trees of the Battery., 1876 (Offsite-box 1)
  - Subseries I.6: HAAS, Richard
    - View of 55th and 5th Avenue, 1977 (Offsite-box 3)
  - Subseries I.7: LOWELL, Nat (1880-1956)
    - Hanover Square, 1851, circa 1948 (Offsite-box 1)
  - Subseries I.8: MEILATZ, Charles (1864-1919)
    - Old Tom's in Thames Street, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Rainy Day Broadway, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Rookeries, Greenwich Village, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Coenties Slip, 1890-1891 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Castle Garden, 1891 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Entrance to Brooklyn Bridge, 1892 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - A Bit of Baxter Street, 1893 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - South Street, from Coenties Slip, 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Oyster Market near Christopher Street (etching), 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - The Aaron Burr House, No. 11 Reade Street (etching), 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Five Points (etching), 1898 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Oyster Market, 1903 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Cherry Street, 1904 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Weehawken Street, 1907 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - Edgar Street, 1910 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - 14th Street, 1912 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - The Tombs, 1889 (Offsite-box 2)
    - The Battery, 1890 (Offsite-box 2)
    - Dewey Triumphal Arch, 1899 (Offsite-box 2)
    - City Hall, 1900 (Offsite-box 2)
    - Catherine Market, 1903 (Offsite-box 2)
    - West Washington Market, 1903 (Offsite-box 2)
    - St. Paul's Church, 1906 (Offsite-box 2)
    - Restaurant in Mott Street, 1906 (Offsite-box 2)
    - Governor Clinton's House (color etching), 1908 (Offsite-box 2)
    - Washington Square (color etching), 1908 (Offsite-box 2)
    - Peck Slip (trial proof second state of plate), 1909 (Offsite-box 2)
    - Whitehall Street, 1909 (Offsite-box 2)
    - Bowling Green (color etching), 1910 (Offsite-box 2)
    - The Butcher's Shop (color etching), 1910 (Offsite-box 2)
    - Bargain Day, 14th Street, 1912 (Offsite-box 2)
    - The Big Tree, 1913-1914 (Offsite-box 2)
  - Subseries I.9: MERSHIMER, Frederick (b. 1958)
    - Old Fulton, 2005 (Offsite-box 1)
    - The Dakota, 2006 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Museum Night, 2008 (Offsite-box 1)
  - Subseries I.10: PELLETTIERI, Michael (b. 1943)
    - It Snowed Again, 1996 (Offsite-box 1)
  - Subseries I.11: PETRULIS, Alan (b. 1954)
    - Broadway at Broome, undated (Offsite-box 1)
    - Howard Street, 1997 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Mercantile Exchange, 1997 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Pearl, 1997 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Broome Street Facades, 1998 (Offsite-box 1)
    - 5th Avenue, 1999 (Offsite-box 1)
    - 125th Street IRT, 1999 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Church, 2002 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Contemplating the Skyline (2), 2003 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Indian Summer, 2008 (Offsite-box 1)
  - Subseries I.12: PONT, Charles Ernest (1898-1971)
    - Peck Slip, 1936 (Offsite-box 1)
  - Subseries I.13: PYZOW, Susan (b. 1955)
    - 7th Avenue South, 2004 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Scheffel Hall at Night, 2008 (Offsite-box 1)
  - Subseries I.14: ROTH, Ernest D. (1879-1964)
    - Union Square, 1924 (Offsite-box 1)
    - Greenwich Village, 1937 (Offsite-box 1)
  - Subseries I.15: TRUEBLOOD, Emily (b. 1942)
    - Empire State Spring, 1998 (Offsite-box 3)
    - Met Lights, 2002 (Offsite-box 3)
    - Subway Lights, 2003 (Offsite-box 3)
    - Snowy Dusk, 2007 (Offsite-box 3)
    - Con Ed Behind Zeckendorf, 2009 (Offsite-box 3)
  - Subseries I.16: WHITE, Charles H. (1878-1918)
    - Fulton Street, 1905 (Offsite-box 1)
- Series II: Commercial Prints
  - Old New York From the Battery to Bloomingdale, etchings by Eliza Greatorex (1875 folio) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-5)
  - Harper's Weekly (tear sheets and full issues), 1862-1897 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6-8)
  - Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper (tear sheets and full issues), 1881-1889 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
  - Tear sheets from other illustrated newspapers, 1896, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)